Michael Moorcock

Free States

Thou still unravish’d bride of quietness,
Thou foster-child of Silence and slow Time,
Sylvan historian, who canst thus express
A flowery tale more sweetly than our rhyme;
What leaf-fringed legend haunts about thy shape
Of deities or mortals or of both,
In Tempe or the dales of Arcady?
What men or gods are these? What maidens loth?
What mad pursuit? What struggle to escape?
What pipes and timbrels? What wild ecstasy?

Keats, Ode on a Grecian Urn

1. LLAMADA DE LAS LEJANAS COLINOS

‘YOU’RE LOOKING BETTER, Jack.’ Sam Oakenhurst has recovered from the machinoix torments. ‘Your old self.’

Jack Karaquazian deals seven hands of poker. His skin reflects a million cultures given up to the pit long before their time; his green eyes reveal a new kind of courtesy. Coolly amiable in his black silk and white linen, his raven hair hanging straight to his shoulders, his back set firmly against that howling triumph of Satan, he is content.

‘I’m feeling it, Sam,’ he says.

~ * ~

Mr Oakenhurst picks up his bags. All around him the outlines and shadows of the Terminal Café shift and caper while Boudreaux Ramsadeen practises a graceful figure with Fathima Panosh, the tiny dancer currently favoured by the Terminal’s regulars who come to hear real old-fashioned zee and witness the purity of the high games. Only at Biloxi, where the Fault yells and ululates, can enough colour be tapped to push new limits. And for those who lose too much, there is always the Fault itself, restless and demanding, greedy for energy and offering, perhaps, an ultimate wisdom.

‘On your way, Sam?’ Jack Karaquazian sits back from his game. His fellow players know him as Al-Q’areen. They are shades, men and women ready to risk everything to win nothing but the approval of their peers. They have the dedicated, ascetic appearance of a strict order. The Egyptian smiles, a kindly jackal.

‘On my way.’ Mr Oakenhurst sets his broad-brimmed pale Panama, dusts at his fine cord travelling coat, his buckskin riding boots, his blue cotton shirt and breeches. ‘So long.’

‘Nobody knows what’s going on up there now,’ says Boudreaux Ramsadeen from the dance floor, his brutish face clouded with concern. ‘They say it’s nothing but vapour up in the Frees. Turned all to steam, mon ami. You be better off staying here.’

Mr Oakenhurst lifts a hand to show appreciation. ‘Estrella errante, vieux pard. You know how it is.’

But Boudreaux Ramsadeen will never know how that is. He brought his Café on the train from Meridian to take advantage of the tourist trade. Now he and the Terminal are married to the Fault until the end of time.

(We are all echoes of some lost original, she would tell him. But we are not diminished by this knowledge. Rather, we are strengthened by it.)

2. SE ERES RAPIDO DISPARA

WHEN MR SAM Oakenhurst took off for the Free States he had it in mind to heal the memories and still the cravings of his last six seasons at the mercy of New Orleans’ infamous machinoix, whose final act of trust was to introduce him to the long, complex mutilation rituals they believed to be the guarantee of continuing existence in the afterlife.

Ending his stopover at the Terminal Café, where Jack Karaquazian still wagered the highest psychic stakes from what had become known as the Dead King’s Chair, his stoic back against the whirling patterns of Chaos ceaselessly forming and reforming, Mr Oakenhurst was at last able to ask his old friend how things went for him.

‘Not so bad now, Sam, pretty good.’

‘You’re looking better, Jack. Your old self.’

~ * ~

‘I’m feeling it, Sam.’ Jack Karaquazian’s fingers moved abstractedly around the dormant dimensions of a waiting flat game. The other players were unhappy with this interruption but unwilling to risk the Egyptian’s displeasure. He toyed with the dealing plates, himself anxious to begin the next hand. And his eyes looked upon so many simultaneous memories.

Before he walked to the door, Sam Oakenhurst said: ‘Come up there with me, Jack. They got some famous spots in Texas and New Mexico. They’re finding colour every day in California. Don’t you want to visit San Diego while she’s still burning? They say you can walk in and out of those flames and feel no heat at all. There’s people still living in the city, completely unhurt. That’s something to see, Jack.’

Mr Karaquazian wished his friend luck in the West but reckoned he had a game or two left to play at the Terminal. In answer to Sam Oakenhurst’s glare of honest surprise, he recalled the old intimacy of their friendship and said, in words only Mr Oakenhurst heard, ‘I can’t go yet.’ He was not ready to speak of his reasons but if his friend were to ride by again at a later time he promised he would tell what happened after they had parted in the Quarter, when the Egyptian had gone upriver on the Memphis boat.

Mr Oakenhurst tipped his hat to his friend and went to collect his horse from Boudreaux’s makeshift stables.

(Have you heard of the conspiracy of the Just? she would ask. Once the likes of us becomes aware of this conspiracy, we are part of it. There’s no choice in the matter. We are, after all, what we are. And you and I, Sam, are of the Just. You don’t have to like it.)

In common with most who chanced their luck at the gambling trade, Sam Oakenhurst had left his will with the Terminal’s neanderthal proprietor. He took the one good horse he had ridden in on, the sound of Boudreaux’s zeeband still marking the rhythm of his actions.

He was almost in the ruins of Picayune before the tunes had left his head. On his way up, he had seen two corpses, a man’s and a woman’s, half buried in the shallows of the beach; behind them was the distant wall of the Biloxi Fault, howling and groaning and never still.

Picayune was the closest Mr Oakenhurst would let himself get to New Orleans. He had no fear of machinoix enmity. They regarded him as one of their own. But he had found a dark new greed in himself which tempted him back to their stronghold.

Mr Oakenhurst did not feel in any way free of the hunger until he entered the twilight fern forests beyond Nouveaux Iberie. His horse followed a broad, dry road, well-marked and patrolled by the local security committees who guaranteed the safety of all who lived there, or passed through peacefully, and swift death to any aggressor.

Sam Oakenhurst’s plan was to take the road right up past Sulphur. He stopped for the night at a lodging house just above Lake Charles where he was met by the landlord, a veteran of the First Psychic War, his skin scaled with pale unstable colour. Lieutenant Twist said that the road now ran up to De Quincey, beside the Texas Waters, a recent series of connected lochs populated by islands stretching almost as far as Houston and nearly up to Dallas. There were a few paddle-wheelers carrying passengers through the lakes but they were infrequent and unscheduled. Mr Oakenhurst was advised to return to New Orleans and buy a ticket on a coastal schoomer to Corpus Cristi. ‘There’s a weekly run. Calmest and safest waters in the world now. They say all the ocean around the Fault’s like that.’

Mr Oakenhurst said he had decided to take his chances. ‘In that case,’ said Lieutenant Twist, ‘you would be better trying for De Quincey and hope a boat or a colour-rider come in soon.’ He shook his head in admiration of what he understood to be Mr Oakenhurst’s bravery. ‘Somebody help me get out of Louisiana, help me get to Houston town!’ Whistling, he led Sam Oakenhurst to the choice individual accommodation behind the old main building.

Making himself presentable Mr Oakenhurst went, after half-an-hour, to join an acoustic game in a corner of the hotel’s bar, but after a few minutes he grew bored and deliberately let the other players win back most of their stakes, keeping five piles noires as payment for his time. On his way to his cabin he saw a movement high up where the fronds were thinnest and the moonlight was turned to pale jade, some sort of owl. Its eyes were huge and full of hope.

Sam Oakenhurst’s chamber was clean, well kept, though the furniture was old and the bedding darned. A useless V-cabinet stood in the comer. Converted to hold magazines, it dispensed them in return for a few pennies. The magazines were hand-coloured, crudely stencilled versions of old-time V programmes. Mr Oakenhurst put in the coins and the screen opened to offer him a selection.

They were chiefly magazines detailing the escapades of various unfamiliar heroes and heroines - The Merchant Venturer, Pearl Peru - Captain Billy Bob Begg’s Famous Chaos Engineers - Karl Kapital - Professor Pop - Fearless Frank Force - Bullybop - Corporal Pork - violently coloured attempts to reproduce the interactive video melodramas some addicts still enjoyed at the Terminal Café. All the characters seemed engaged in perpetual war between Plurality and Singularity for the domination of a territory (possibly philosophical) called the Second Ether. These unlikely events were represented as fact. The gambler, finding their enigmatic vocabularies and queer storylines too cryptic, replaced them in the dispenser, blew out his lamp and slept, dreaming a familiar dream.

(He had talked to Jack Karaquazian when they were still in New Orleans. He had asked his friend if he would care if he spoke of something that was on his mind.

“Not at all,” the Egyptian had said.

I had this dream, said Sam Oakenhurst. I was standing on this cliff with a pack of dogs and killer blankeys at my back and nothing but rocks and ocean far below and nowhere to go but down when suddenly out of the blue this golden limo pulls up in the air right where I’m standing on the edge and the driver’s eye-balling me. She’s a beautiful woman, real elegant, and she says “Hop in, Sam. Where do you want to go?”

“Where are you going?” I ask.

“Any place you like,” she says.

“Well,” I say, “I guess in that case I’ll stick here and take my chances.”

“Please yourself,” she says and she’s ready to start up when I say “Hey, what’s your name, lady?”

“Luck,” she says, puts the car in gear and vanishes. I turn around and the dogs and the men are gone. What do you make of that, Jack?

“Well,” said Jack Karaquazian after some considerable thought, “I guess it means that luck is luck. That’s all.”

“I guess so,” said Mr Oakenhurst. “Well, goodnight, Jack.”

Next morning they played a game of Joli Jean before breakfast and talked about going up to the Frees.)

He had the dream again, exactly as before, but this time he stepped into the limo.

(Jack Karaquazian kept a room above the main casino of the Terminal Café. You could feel the zee coming up through the floor. The room was filled with shadows and flames, ragged holes of verdigris and kidney. “It’s home,” he had said.)

3. ERASE UNA VEZ EN LA OUESTE

‘I HAD A dream,’ says Precious Mary as she moves against Sam Oakenhurst’s arm. ‘I dreamed I was lying in this field of silver poppies looking up at the moon. I stretched my arms and legs wide and the Moon Goddess smiled. She had a wonderful round pale oriental face like a Buddha. Is that a Buddhess, Sam? And she came down from the midnight blue and pursed her silver lips and she sucked my pussy, Sam, like nobody but you.’ She grins and laughs and slaps at him in his flattered embarrassment.

~ * ~

They had been here at Ambry’s for almost a month. Precious Mary was on her way to join a closed order in Laredo. She collected mosquitoes and her little clear envelopes were full of the different types, including the hybrids. Her pride was a great dragon mosquito, rainbow carapace over two inches long, able to drain a small rodent dry of blood in less than a minute. ‘They thought it carried A,’ she said. ‘But now they ain’t so sure.’

She had cornrows beaded with tiny precious stones - emeralds, rubies, sapphires, diamonds - large green eyes, a refined Watutsi face. She wore a silk shift which swam on the blackness of her skin like milk over marble. Her head, she said, was worth a million guineas, but her body was priceless. She lived, like everyone in De Quincey, at Ambry’s big Gothic timber house just by the jetty which jutted over the flat sheen of a lake revealed below the surrounding yellow and black mist. The lake was never entirely at rest. Shapes just under the surface were mysterious and alarming. Every once in a while a tiny spot of colour would float by. ‘They find big ones out there and milk them,’ she said. ‘There’s nothing but rigs once you get twenty kays over that horizon.’ She pointed to the north. ‘Do you believe in God, Sam?’

Mr Oakenhurst admitted that he did.

‘You believe in a just God, Sam?’

‘I believe God deals you a fair hand.’ He became thoughtful. ‘What you do with it after that is a question of luck and judgement both. And luck is what other people are making of their hands. It’s a complicated game, it seems to me, Mary. Only a few of us are willing to accept the kind of odds it offers. But what else can you do? This is reality, I think. I look at the game. I work out the odds. And then I decide if I want to play or not. I hope I’m doing no more or less with my mind and time than God expects of me.’

‘You’re crazy,’ she said.

That was the last Sam Oakenhurst and Precious Mary ever spoke of religion.

In Milton he had lost his horse to a tall pile broker from Natchez who had proved to be so much better than the table’s other partners that Mr Oakenhurst suspected him of being a secret professional. But he had played a fair game. The broker let Sam take his place on the coach to De Quincey. That trip to the lake shore had been Mr Oakenhurst’s first real experience of the practical realities of the Free States, where whites were supposed to be his equals. He found it awkward to be travelling in a horse-drawn coach with a black man driving and a white man riding inside. On the seat across from him the “bianco” showed no similar embarrassment and chatted amiably on the tandem subjects of fluke attractors and the availability of piles noires. Mr Oakenhurst did his best to converse without seeming to condescend, but he was still suffering from a strong desire to stare in wonder at this educated and self-confident whitey much as one would regard a clever circus animal. His name was Peewee Wilson and he had owned property up in Haute County, he said, until it had popped one morning, all of a piece, and left him “wiv a weird damned hole coloured like dirty bottly-glass an’ radiatin’ coldness so damned bad ah’d felt mahse’f chillered to mah soul.” He had moved his wife and kids to his sister in San Diego and was on his way to join them. He had never been to Biloxi (“Ah have not chosered vat pilgrimage, sah, as yet.”) but was eager to hear Mr Oakenhurst’s account of it and the jugador loved to tell a tale.

So the time had passed pleasantly enough between Milton and De Quincey. Peewee informed Mr Oakenhurst about the famous Colossus of Tarzana, one of the wonders of their new world - a huge figure some two hundred feet high and apparently consisting of living flame which gave off a soft heat filling most observers with a sense of calm and well-being. A tent town had grown around the feet of the Colossus, populated by those who had become hooked on the phenomenon’s influence.

(Let us have the body, the machinoix would demand. We need it for our science. Its soul has dissipated. What use is it to you? But Sam Oakenhurst would refuse to give it up. He would take it with him all the way to the Fault and pitch it in. The machinoix would not be offended. He was of their number. He could do no wrong, save betray another of their own.)

Mr Oakenhurst waded through the shallow mud of the lake shore. There seemed no end to it. At present the flat, troubled liquid reflected nothing, but every so often a shape threatened to break through the surface. The clouds had become a solid monochrome grey. Once in a while a long thread of bright scarlet would rise from below the horizon and give the sky a lizard’s lick. Mr Oakenhurst ran secret fingers over his most intimate scars. His longing for the past was like physical hunger. A madness. He prayed for a vessel to rescue him.

Mr Oakenhurst walked through the mud. Sometimes his legs would begin to tremble, threatening to give out completely, and he would panic, turning slowly to look back at Ambry’s and the long, dark jetty whose far point penetrated the mist.

‘Darling.’ Precious Mary led him home on these occasions.

‘Darling, Sam.’

Sam Oakenhurst decided that if he stayed another week he would take it as a sign and let New Orleans call him back. He shivered. He had made no real decision at all. He glared at the grey water. The sky, he thought, had turned the colour of rotten honey.

4. LA MUERTE TERRIO UN PRECIO

PRECIOUS MARY WAS not impatient to leave. She had discovered an interest in the vegetable garden and, with another woman called Bellpai’s, was planting in the assumption there would be some kind of new season. The garden lay behind the house, where it was most sheltered. Mary complained about the lack of sunlight, the clouds of dust which swam forever out of the north. ‘It seems like it’s the same clouds keep coming around,’ she said. ‘Like everything’s on repeat.’

‘Hope not,’ said Sam Oakenhurst, thinking of New Orleans. As a child he had played his favourite records until the phonograph’s machinery had started to show the strain. Gradually the voices grew sluggish and the music became a mixture of whines and groans until finally the records brought only depression, a sense of loss, a distorted memory of harmony and resolution. He sometimes thought the whole world was running down in a series of ever-widening, steadily dissipating circles. ‘I cannot believe that one thing cancels out another,’ he admitted to Precious Mary.

‘It’s like a roof.’ She looked at the sky. ‘Like a cave. We could be underground, Sam. Living on the innards of the world.’

Across the surface of measureless grey, past the end of their jetty, a couple of spots of colour floated. The spots moved as if with purpose but both Mr Oakenhurst and Precious Mary knew they drifted more or less at random around the perimeter of the lake, carrying with them an assortment of organic flotsam. Bones, feathers, twigs, tiny corpses made a lattice through which gleamed the dull gold and silver of the colour, blank round eyes staring out from a void. The colour seemed like a magnet to certain vegetable and animal matter. Other material it repulsed violently, not always predictably.

(We are the whole within the whole, Sam. Your ancestors knew that. And we are unique.)

‘I reckon Jack Karaquazian struck colour up on the Trace,’ mused Sam Oakenhurst. ‘But something happened that didn’t suit him. What the hell is that, Mary?’ He pointed out over the lake. Through the twilight a slow bulky shape was emerging. At first the jugador thought it might be the tapering head of a large whale. Then as it came nearer he realized it was not a living creature at all but a ramshackle vessel, shadowing the shore, a great broad raft about ninety by ninety, on which was built a floating shanty-town, a melange of dull-coloured shacks, tents, barrels and lean-tos. In the middle of this makeshift floating fortress stood a substantial wooden keep with a flat roof where other tents and packing-case houses had been erected so that the whole had the appearance of an untidy ziggurat made of animal hides, old tapestries, painted canvases, upholstery and miscellaneous pieces of broken furniture.

Observing what distinguished this floating junkpile, Precious Mary said: ‘Ain’t that queer, Sam. No metal, not much plastic ... ‘

‘And there’s why.’ Sam showed her the dull gleam of colour spilling up from under the raft’s edges. ‘She’s moving on a big spot. She’s built to cover it. You saw it. That kind of colour won’t take anything much that’s non-organic. It’s kind of like anti-electricity. They haven’t figured any real way of conducting the stuff. It can’t be refined or mined. It moves all the time so it’s never claimed. I guess these types have found the only use there is for it. Ahoy!’

5. MUCHOS GRACIAS, MON AMOUR

THE IDEA OF being trapped on a raft which would put the Texas Waters between him and New Orleans was immensely attractive to Mr Oakenhurst just then. There was no way of stopping the spot, only of slowing it down with metal lures floated out from the shore on lines. As soon as the goods had been thrown aboard, he jumped from the jetty to the slow-moving deck, shook hands with Captain Roy Ornate, master of The Whole Hog, and thanked him for the opportunity to take passage with him. He did not bother to announce his trade.

He had been allowed to carry no arms aboard The Whole Hog, no razor, no metal of any kind except alumite, and so glad was he to be on his way that he had accepted the terms, leaving his gold, his piles noires, his slender Nissan 404 and all other metal goods with Precious Mary. She had loaded the raft with so much collateral in the form of fresh provisions that she had put him in excellent credit with Captain Ornate. The bandy-legged pig-faced upriver rafter had lost his original trade to the Colorado Gap. ‘Took the river and half the State with it. You can still see the spray fifty kays away.’ He was a cheerful man who apologized for his rules. His methods were the only practical ones for the service he offered, which was, he admitted, not much. ‘Still, chances are this spot’ll carry us round to Waco and you’re halfway to Phoenix, or wherever it is you’re heading, mister. You won’t be old when you get there, but I can’t guarantee how long it will take ...

‘You won’t be bored, either, mister. There’s a couple of jugaderos in the main saloon glad to make room for another. This is an easy vessel, Mr Oakenhurst, and 1 hope you’ll find her comfortable. She’s rough and ready, I’ll grant, but we have no power weapons aboard and hardly any violence, for I don’t tolerate trouble. Those who make it I punish harshly.’

‘A man of my own principles, captain,’ said Sam Oakenhurst, conscious of the loss of his fancy links. His shirt was heavier on the wrists, the cuffs now decorated with antique Mickey and Minnie Mouse figures his daughter had given him for his twenty-fifth birthday, almost exactly forty-four seasons ago, and which he had never expected to wear in public. Now that the need had arisen he welcomed it. Wearing the links felt like some sort of confirmation. Serdia and Ona had died together on the Hattiesburg Roar, trying to escape an army of half-wild blankeys released by a shiver from the nearby pens. He had been in Memphis, running a powered game for Peabody and his fellow barons who could command all the necessary colour. He had been unable to resist.

Mr Oakenhurst had never known the detailed circumstances of his wife’s and daughter’s deaths and time had put that particular pain behind him. He sensed some link between his grief and his taste for machinoix torments. He had never, after all, thought to blame himself for the deaths. They had wanted to remain in Hattiesburg where everyone agreed it felt pretty stable. For a while he had wished he could die, too, that was all. Maybe he felt guilty for not following them.

He let Roy Ornate’s little kiddikin lead him up the rickety outside staircase to his room. The urge to live was very strong in Sam Oakenhurst and not quite equalled by an urge for pain which he only barely governed these days. With relief he watched the jetty and the Ambry House slip away behind, but the look he turned on the kiddikin, even as the skinny white kid glowingly accepted a whole guinea bill for his trouble, was one of vicious and unjust hatred.

Sam Oakenhurst came out of his room and looked down at the smoking stoves and basket fires of a floating slum. Roy Ornate was waiting at the bottom of the stairs. ‘Why do these people live in such squalor, captain, when, on land, they have a better chance of dignity?’ Were they all power addicts?

Captain Ornate cleared his throat. ‘If you’re trying to fathom the pilgrims, Mr Oakenhurst, you’ll have poor luck. If you’re dining this evening, I’d welcome your company.’ He spoke with no great enthusiasm. Sam Oakenhurst guessed that Roy Ornate was not really his own man and that there was another power aboard The Whole Hog greater than the master.

6. Ml BUENA SUERTE

THE SALOON WAS on the lower floor, a big, bright room full of old-fashioned wooden Kenya-lamps and carved candelabra. On the other side of the archway, in relative gloom, five people were absorbed in a complex game of Hunt the Moth, their eyes golden with concentration as they fanned their acoustic hands with practised pseudo-electronic signals, listening intensely to the subsonics.

(In times like these, when hope fades and our expectations of reality become uncertain, people develop a keen interest in an afterlife, she said. She sang to him in a language he did not know. He begged her to translate. “We are trapped in the glare of their headlights,” she said.)

Elsewhere in the saloon men and women in couples or groups sat together drinking and talking, but it was clear that pains were taken not to disturb the five gamblers as they strove to simulate the serial-linking, the empathetic convolutions, the exquisite arabesques of the powered original.

Looking again at the jugaderos, Sam Oakenhurst knew at once who was the real master of The Whole Hog. Fat body pulsing, he or she sat facing the room. The head, to one side, was hidden by a queerly shaped mask and old dust seemed to fall from its folds. The pale eyes glittered like over-polished diamonds. The top of the creature’s head was scarred and pitted, as if by fire, and a few tufts of grey-black hair sprouted here and there, while a little multicoloured bead curtain, some bizarre chadurrah, hung from the bottom edge of its mask, obscuring the jaw. The only flesh visible was the ruined crown and a pair of large, white hands which also bore the grey scars of fire and sat poised on their tips like obscene tarantulas, pale with menace.

The masked figure was, on its right, flanked by a light-skinned, but otherwise handsome, half-caste woman with greased black ringlets and hard Irish eyes. Her name was Sister Honesty Marvell. She was persona non grata at the Terminal, for taking out an amateur in a massive psychic gambit which even broke the high limits Boudreaux Ramsadeen set for the professionals. When he had made her go for good she had sworn she would return and the second Boudreaux saw her would be the second he died.

(En la playa, amigo, replied Amos Gallibasta when Sam Oakenhurst found him again and asked how he was. The thin giant had grinned, death’s triumph, and snapped his huge fingers. En la playa terminante, eh? Joli blanc! Joli blanc! He had no similar desire to return to New Orleans. The very breathing of the word “machinoix” sent him into uncontrollable fits of vomiting.)

Next to Sister Honesty sat Carly O’Dowd. Mr Oakenhurst also knew her. Mrs O’Dowd sported a man’s suit in the Andalusian style and as always bore an air of disdainful self-sufficiency. Her Moorish good looks reminded Mr Oakenhurst of some legendary toreador. He tipped his hat when she looked up but she could not see beyond her strategies. The two players at the other side of the enmascaro were people Sam Oakenhurst recognized. He could name only one. Popper Hendricks, sagging with the weight of a thousand indulgences, had once been a famous zeestar in the days when touring was still possible, when the population was considerably larger, and when records were still being made. Fifty percent at least of the white minority had fled north or west after the Fault’s effects began to be felt. Even many middle-class people had preferred to go west into the Frees to take their chances on equal terms with the whites, but mostly got caught by the quakes. Hendricks had the sybaritic, bloated look of a heavy oper. The other man, with his huge square head, had the features of an Aztec god. Even his body seemed made of granite. He moved now, slowly. It was as if ten years went by. Mr Oakenhurst found the Indian disturbing but the masked man at the centre of the game horrified him.

In shape the mask resembled a map of the old US. Each State, cut out of an alumite can, had been soldered to the next. Washington bore the distinctive logo of Folger’s Coffee, Texas offered RC Cola and Pennsylvania advertised EXXON oil. From the patchwork of pseudo-metal were suspended the heavy beads, veiling a suggestion of red, wet lips, skin as burned and scarred as the hands and skull.

Mr Oakenhurst turned his back on the table to order a Jax from the bartender, a round-faced whitey who proved unduly surly. To be civil, Sam Oakenhurst asked, ‘What’s your name, boy?’

‘Burt,’ said the whitey curtly. ‘You want another beer, mister?’

Mr Oakenhurst kept his own council. After all, he could soon be facing much more of this behaviour in the Free States and he had best get used to it. He intended to relax. For the first time since he had left the Terminal he no longer depended upon his own will. Whatever problems he found upon the raft, he thought, must seem minor. He was glad there were no power weapons permitted, though he missed the comfort of his Nissan.

From the shadows in the back of the big room came a sudden wheeze, a whine, and an accordion began to play Pierrot, Pierrot, le monde estfou. Some of the passengers swayed to the old tune, singing the poet Armangal’s sad, ironic words. Le monde estfou, my carazon d’or. Le monde estfou, el mundo c’est moi!

A voice from the table, soft and threatening, said ‘Play something else, dear.’

The tune changed almost instantly to Two-Step de Bayou Teche and a few of the couples got up to dance.

The masked man returned his attention to the game.

7. DESAFIO

‘MR MINCT AND me came aboard at Carthage,’ said Carly O’Dowd. She referred to the masked man, still playing. ‘Nice to see you, Sam.’

‘And you, Carly. How’s the game?’

‘Worth your time, if you’re interested.’ She was taking a break and joined Captain Ornate and Mr Oakenhurst at their table. ‘Some rough edges you could smooth out.’ She reached for his long right hand and drew it to her mouth. ‘Lucky, Sam?’ She kissed the tip of his index finger.

‘Maybe,’ he said. ‘I don’t know.’

Roy Ornate had grown expansive on his big pipe of ope. His cheeks glowed, his eyes bulged with bonhomie. ‘I can think of no better pleasure than swinging your feet over the edge of the Abyss and contemplating the damnation of the entire universe,’ he confided. ‘Ha, ha, Mr Oakenhurst. You’ll do!’ His confidences became increasingly mysterious. ‘What a thrill, eh? To take the whole damned vessel to the edge - cargo, crew and passengers - and hang upon the lip of some hellish niagara - every day gambling the same stake against a thousand new disasters - all the devil’s winning hands - and every day carry back from the brink - what? Playing dice with God and not a damned thing any of you fellows can do about it. I know the only man good enough to stop this planet going the way of the rest and that’s Paul Minct, and he won’t do it. I would, but I can’t. And that, sir, should permit me a few privileges…’

Neither Mr Oakenhurst nor Mrs O’Dowd could follow his reasoning.

‘You have a great admiration for this Mr Minct,’ said Sam Oakenhurst.

‘He’s my hero,’ admitted Captain Ornate with a confiding gesture.

Now the Indian Carly O’Dowd had identified as Rodrigo Heat divorced himself from the game and moved heavily over the floor to stand beside an empty chair next to Captain Ornate.

Sam Oakenhurst received the impression that the masked man had sent Heat to him. The Indian’s massive head inclined towards the seat but his eyes were on Carly O’Dowd. ‘You have a high price, lady, but that don’t scare me.’

Sam Oakenhurst knew only one way of responding to such boorishness and his words were out before he had properly calculated the situation. He said evenly that if Mr Heat pursued that thread of conversation he would be obliged to invite the Indian outside to the place familiarly known as - and here he looked to Captain Ornate to tell him the name again ...

‘Bloody Glade,’ said Roy Ornate, still benign. ‘But we discourage its use. This M&E is better than my own.’ He was trying a mixture, he said, recommended by Paul Minct. He displayed a garish package: Meng & Ecker’s Brandy Flake.

‘Bloody Glade,’ said Mr Oakenhurst, ‘and settle the matter alia gentilhombres.’

Whereupon Mr Heat laughed open-mouthed and asked what was wrong with his conversation.

Understanding, now, that he was being provoked, Sam Oakenhurst could only continue. His honour gave him no choice. ‘It demeans a lady,’ he explained.

Mr Heat continued to laugh and asked where the lady in question happened to be, which led to a silence falling in the room, since Mr Oakenhurst’s principles, if not his courage, were shared by the majority of the floor’s diamentes brutos.

‘Very well,’ said Mr Oakenhurst after a moment. ‘I will meet you in the usual circumstances,’ and as if he had settled some minor matter he turned back to signal the surly whitey for more drinks and enquire of Carly O’Dowd how her brother was doing in the Border Army. ‘Ain’t they romantic, Carly? I heard they’re winning big new tracts of restabilized up above Kansas.’

‘You’re a man after my own heart, sir,’ suddenly says Captain Ornate, puffing on his churchwarden’s. ‘Would you care for a dip from my special mixture?’ He reached into his coat.

‘Give him my Meng & Ecker’s, Captain Ornate.’

Paul Minct’s cruel voice chilled the house into irredeemable silence.

‘Give Mr Oakenhurst a dip of my own ope and ask him if, at his convenience, he would come to join me later for a chat. It’s rare to meet an equal, these days. One grows so starved of intellectual cut and thrust.’

8. GRACIAS NADA MAS

‘CABALLERO AND MUKHAMIR, you may be, Mr Oakenhurst, of the highest principles and most excellent suba’, but Captain Ornate allows no desafio aboard The Whole Hog and so your affair must be abandoned until such time you are both ashore. Those are Captain Ornate’s rules.’ Paul Minct speaks with a certain weariness.

Sam Oakenhurst now understands that he has been tested and that his honour is not at issue. He shrugs the matter off.

They sit together in the snug in the back shadows, a candle burning on the table giving unsteady life to Paul Minct’s geographic mask.

Mr Oakenhurst finds himself reading the fragments of words - ELMONTE, OLA, AX WELL HOU, CRISCO, CASTRO, ONT MAID, OHNSONS WAX and others - remembering his childhood when such brands were vital and had complex and casual meaning to everyone. The world’s realities changed, he thinks, long before the advent of the Fault. The Fault is perhaps the result of that change, not the cause. He cannot give his entire attention to Paul Minct’s words. The man disturbs and fascinates him. He gathers Paul Minct respects him, which is why he has been taken aside like this and not admonished in public, and he is relieved. But he knows he could never trust the enmascaro. Paul Minct could change his mood at a moment’s notice and casually kill him. Sam Oakenhurst is close to admitting he made a mistake. He should have found the nerve to stick it out at Ambry’s until the stem-wheeler came by. His self-disgust only serves to fuel his discomfort. He wishes the enmascaro would leave him alone, but already guesses Mr Minct plans somehow to use him.

(Paul Minct had been a blankey-chaser in the old days, Carly O’Dowd said. Mr Minct had gone after bounty boys, always willing to take a dead-or-alive. One day he had crossed the big bridge into Louisiana with six red scalps on his belt, all that was mortal of the Kennedy pack which ran wild for a while up near Texarcana and announced they’d founded a “white republic”. Captain Ornate retired. Mrs O’ Dowd called for more drinks. ‘Paul Minct’s a man who gets what or who he wants, one way or another,’ she said. ‘He was Peabody’s main chaser. He hates whiteys with a passion and would wipe them all out if he could. He loathes them so bad some of us think maybe he’s a blankey himself, or anyway a breed, who was fortunate enough to be burned in a fire - like the blankey who went to hell, got burned black and thought he’d gotten to heaven! Loosen up, Sam. Nothing much ever happens on The Whole Hog.’)

‘I was in a bad fire or two in my time, Mr Oakenhurst.’ Paul Minct fingers the tufts of hair on his skull. ‘You should hear my wife complain. But someone has to bring home the bacon. We’re the chaps who have to get out there in the world, eh? Nobody will do it for us. We are never allowed nor encouraged to the best. That’s the shame of it. We must seek the best for ourselves. It is what drives us, I suspect. Almost secretly. Will you be joining our little pasatiempo? You’d be very welcome.’

When Mr Oakenhurst accepts the veiled order with the same grace with which it is given, one of Paul Minct’s unsightly hands reaches into his and welcomes him to the school.

(‘He told me he had been in and out of the Fault five times. He says he knows secret trails which only he had the courage to discover. It is true that in the main he has no fear.’

‘Does he fear anything, Carly?’

‘Something. I don’t know. Is there a jugador brave enough to find out?’) Paul Minct offers his own pouch. ‘A cut above the Brandy Rake. It’s M&E’s Number Three. They’ll try to tell you it’s extinct, but they’re still making it down in Mexico.’

Against his better judgement, Sam Oakenhurst fills his long-stemmed pipe.

‘Señor Heat is an old colleague of mine. ‘ Paul Minct receives the ope again and puts it away. ‘Volatile and blunt, as you know, and a little uncouth, but one of the world’s great people He discovered the factory. The last Meng & Ecker’s is in a place called Wadi-al-Hara, the River of Stones, in Arabic. The Indian dialects give it a similar name. Guadalajara, the Spanish say. Mr Heat made his second fortune bringing it back. This stuff’s what the old days were about, Mr Oakenhurst. Not much of a vice compared to some we hear of. That’s what I remind my wife. She’s overly worried. My health. That’s women for you, isn’t it? My health, as a matter of fact, has never been better. But there you are. Now, Mr Oakenhurst, I know your credentials and I must say I’m impressed. How would you like to come in on a small venture I’m organizing?’

‘Well, sir,’ says Sam Oakenhurst. ‘I guess it depends on the game.’

‘Very good, Mr Oakenhurst. I take your point. This is in the nature of an exploratory expedition. But only the likes of us can even contemplate the kind of expedition I have in mind. Only a trained jugador has the patience, the experience and the gumption for it. And Mrs O’Dowd says you’re one of the best. Played evens with Jack Karaquazian.’

‘Once,’ agrees Sam Oakenhurst.

‘Quite enough for me, sir. I’m recruiting, Mr Oakenhurst, a few brave souls. Outstanding individuals who will join an expedition to accompany me into the Biloxi Fault.’

Sam Oakenhurst has a taste for pain but not for death. He resolves to play along with this madman whose pale unblinking eye awaits his acceptance, but if the time comes he will never go with him. That would be suicide. He will jump off the raft the first moment they sight land and put this fresh lunacy behind him.

He shakes Paul Minct’s hand.

9. ESCUDO D’ORO

MR SAM OAKENHURST did not immediately join the game but claiming weariness retired early and stood on the little landing outside his door taking the ill-smelling air and staring over the dark water. No light escaped the spot on which they rode, but through the dirty cloud a little moonlight fell, making the water sinister with half-seen shapes.

In seeking to avoid the machinoix temptations Mr Oakenhurst had put himself into an equally unwelcome predicament. Paul Minct had a horrible authority and, taken unawares, Sam Oakenhurst had been unable to resist it.

Tomorrow he would test Mr Minct’s metal, if he could, in that acoustic game they played, and get some notion of the man’s resonances. He had not been manipulated so expertly since he was fourteen. He believed Paul Minct to be a charlatan, probably crazy, perhaps even messianic in some way. Frequently a secret faith, too insane to risk upon the air, fuelled such aggressive solipsism. The man appeared to have the tastes of a Torquemada and the savage appetites of a European warlord. Always a strong hand, thought Mr Oakenhurst. His lies would therefore be complicated and self-convincing. Mr Oakenhurst had lived for months at a time beside the Fault and knew it well. He had seen a woman from Jackson walk in at the semipermanent section known as The Custard Bowl and disintegrate, bawling for help, as soon as she reached the so-called East Wall, a turbulent tower sometimes emerging within the Bowl, usually coloured deep red and black. On another occasion he had held a rope for Cab Ras, the famous daredevil, as he went in through the glistening organic scarlet of Ketchup Cave. He had vanished. The rope had fallen to the surface as if cut and Ras was gone for good. Everything was consumed by the Biloxi Fault. Was Paul Minct merely reluctant to die alone?

Mr Oakenhurst did not doubt the enmascaro’s courage or ferocity, the man’s murderous determination, but could not fathom Paul Minct’s objectives. Perhaps Mr Minct had actually convinced himself that he could survive the Fault, and others with him. It was not a belief Mr Oakenhurst wished to put to the test. Yet, for all his evident insanity, the man continued to terrify Sam Oakenhurst who wondered if Paul Minct already had his measure, as he did not have Mr Minct’s. A game would answer most of his questions. He was no Jack Karaquazian, but he had held his own with the rest.

Most of the lights were now extinguished to conform with Captain Ornate’s tough curfew, enforced by a gang of breed blankey’s under their own vicious leaders.

The raft rocked a little in the water and a powerful shaft of moonlight broke through full on The Whole Hog as if God for a moment had turned his undivided attention on them. A voice came up to him out of the shadows. ‘Time for bed, Sam?’

‘Good evening, Carly.’ Sam Oakenhurst wanted to learn all she knew of Paul Minct. ‘I’ve a bottle of Arkwright’s I know you’ll taste.’

~ * ~

Carly O’Dowd had little more real information. She remembered a story that Paul Minct’s hatred of whites could be relatively recent, following a fire started by his own relatives from Baton Rouge. But there was a different story of how Paul Minct had been a member of the Golala sect which believed death by fire was a guarantee of heaven. She asked Sam if he believed in an afterlife.

‘I have a hunch your soul has a home to go to. ‘ That was all Sam Oakenhurst would say on the matter, but when she asked if he believed God dealt everyone a square hand, he shook his head. He had thought about that lately, he said. He had to admit that God’s dealing sometimes seemed a little uneven.

‘But I don’t think he plays dice, Carly. He plays a hand of poker against the devil and some of us believe it’s our job to help him. Some of us even do a little bit about it.’ He shrugged.

‘Jesus,’ said Carly O’Dowd. ‘I never heard anyone describe gambling as a moral duty before. Ain’t this the end of everything, Sam? Ain’t it over for us?’

‘Maybe,’ said Sam Oakenhurst, ‘but I got a feeling it evens out. Like luck, you know.’

Carly O’Dowd took a long pull on the pipe and sipped her winking Arkwright’s.

‘Quid pro quo,’ said Mr Oakenhurst.

‘Allez, los tigres,’ she sang softly. ‘Ma bebe sans merci, il est un majo sin compare. O, be be, you bon surprise, you darling ease.’

In the morning she insisted he come to the open window to look over the ragged shanty town, towards the east where the cloud had cleared and red sunlight rose in broad rays from the watery horizon, staining the whole lake a lively ruby. Against this redness a single black outline moved.

‘It’s coming closer.’ Sam Oakenhurst squinted to improve his focus. ‘It’s a big heron, Carly.’ He shivered. He took her slight body to his. ‘Bigger.’

It was an aircraft. A beautiful white flying boat with six pairs of wing-mounted roaring engines and whistling airscrews, moving to make a preliminary pass at the water, intending to land. The flying boat was turned a sudden, subtle pink by the sun.

Everyone on the raft was up and out in haste to see the splendid craft. Pilgrims and jugaderos all wondered at the wealth it took to squander so much colour upon an antique conceit.

And then, throttling down to a confident thud, the flying boat came to settle, light as a gull, upon the surface. The big engines fell silent. Water lapped at her ivory hull. Almost at once a door above the lower wing opened and a figure stepped out, dragging a small inflatable. The grey rubber boat blended with the leaden waters as black and yellow cloud drew itself round the sun like a cloak. Through the gloom of the new day the figure began to row, calling out in a melodious, ringing voice; ‘Ahoy, the raft! Is this The Whole Hog and Captain Roy Ornate?’

Just up from his quarters in his Monday whites and weak-kneed with wonderment, Captain Ornate could barely lift his megaphone to utter an unsteady; ‘I am Captain Roy Ornate, master of The Whole Hog. Be warned that we accept no metal. Who calls the ship?’

This was a formal exchange, as between river captains. The rower replied. ‘Mrs Rose von Bek, lately out of Guadalajara with a package for Mr Paul Minct. Is Mr Minct aboard, sir?’

The weight of the curious crowd began to tilt the raft dramatically. The shanty dwellers were set upon by the blankeys, led by a plague-pocked overseer, and beaten back into order. To add to their humiliation they were forced into their windowless dwellings, denied any further part of the miracle.

‘Mr Minct is one of our passengers,’ agreed Roy Ornate, his own curiosity undisguised. ‘What’s the nature of your goods, ma’am?’

Before the rower could answer, Paul Minct, massively fat, his body wrapped in lengths of multicoloured velvet, rolled up to Captain Ornate’s side to stand stroking his beaded veil as another might stroke a beard. He took the megaphone from the grateful master and spoke in a wet, amplified soprano. ‘So you found me at last. Is that my M&E come up from Mexico, dear?’

Mr Oakenhurst began to imagine himself back in time, taking part in one of the interactive adventure ads of his childhood. Was this, after all, no more than some misremembered bite?

Any answer Mrs von Bek might have made was drowned by six bellowing engines as the flying boat began to taxi out over the endless grey lake and, with a parting shriek, vanished into the air.

The inflatable came up against embarking-steps thick with mould. A slim, athletic woman stepped aboard, her features disguised by a cowl on her cape which fell in blue-green folds almost to the deck. Maybe a white woman. She had a small oilskin package in her left hand.

By now Mr Oakenhurst and Mrs O’Dowd, fully dressed, stood on the landing listening to the silence returning.

‘I’m much obliged, ma’am.’ Paul Minct reached for his package. ‘One would have to be Scrooge himself to begrudge that extra little bit it takes to get your M&E delivered.’ He turned, his mask on one side, as if in apology to Sam Oakenhurst. ‘I’ll admit it’s a terrible extravagance of mine. You should hear my wife on the subject.’

Had he arranged this whole charade merely to demonstrate his power and wealth?

The woman pushed her cowl back to reveal a most wonderful dark golden pink skin, washed with the faintest browns and greens, some kind of sensitive North African features, reminding Mr Oakenhurst of those aquiline Berbers from the deep Maghribi desert. Her auburn hair reflected the colour of her cloak and her lips were a startling scarlet, as if they bled. She was as tall as Sam Oakenhurst. Her extraordinary grace fascinated him. He had never seen movement like it. He found himself staring at her, even as she took Paul Minct’s arm and made her way to the main saloon.

‘What would you call that colour skin?’ murmured Carly O’Dowd.

10. LOS BELLES DU CANADA

‘I TASTED A thousand scales to reach this place.’ Mrs von Bek had been joined at her table by Sister Honesty Marvell, Mrs O’Dowd and Rodrigo Heat, but she kept a seat beside her empty and this she now offered to Mr Oakenhurst who bowed, brushed back his tails and wished her good morning as he sat down beside her. He wondered why she seemed familiar. At close quarters the greenish blush of her hands, the pink-gold of her cheeks had a quality which made all other flesh seem unnatural. He had never before felt such strong emotion in the presence of beauty.

In amused recognition of his admiration, she smiled. Clearly, she was also curious about him. ‘You are of the jugadiste persuasion, Mr Oakenhurst?’

‘I make a small living from my good fortune, ma’am.’ Had he ever felt as he did now, at the centre of a concert while the music achieved some ecstatic moment? Was he looking on the true face of his lady, his luck? Where would she take him? Home?

He realized to his alarm that he was on the verge of weeping.

‘Well, Mr Oakenhurst,’ Mrs von Bek continued, ‘you would know a flat game, I hope, if one turned up for you. And Granny’s Claw? Is that still played in these parts?’

‘Not to my knowledge, ma’am.’

I need an ally, she said in an urgent signal, which marked her as his peer. Paul Minct is my mortal enemy and will destroy me if he recognizes me. Will you help?

He returned her signal. At your service, Mrs von Bek.

No sworn jugador could have refused her. Their mutual code demanded instant compliance. Only in extreme need did one of his kind thus address a peer. But he would have helped her anyway. He was entirely infatuated with her. He began to wonder what other allies, and of what calibre, he might find here. Did fear or some profound sense of loyalty bind Rodrigo Heat to Paul Minct? Carly O’Dowd, given to sudden swings of affection, would be unreliable at best. Roy Ornate was also Paul Minct’s man. Sister Honesty Marvell might side with them, if only out of an habitual need to destroy potential rivals. Meanwhile, Mr Oakenhurst would have to follow Mrs von Bek’s lead until she told him to do otherwise.

Her fingers dropped from the grey-green pearls and coral at her throat while his own hands lost interest in his links. Their secret exchange was for a moment at an end.

It had been seven years - twenty-eight seasons by current reckoning - since Mr Oakenhurst had been in a similar situation and that had been the start of his friendship with Jack Karaquazian. On this occasion, however, the intellectual thrill, the thrill of the big risk, was coupled with his overwhelming desire for her given extra edge by his own anxious guess that perhaps she was at least a little attracted to him. Even the chemistry with Serdia had not been so strong. The sensation attacked his mind as well as his flesh while the cool part of him, the trained jugador, was taking account of this wonderful return of feelings he had thought lost for ever, and considering new odds.

‘Do you think it will be long before we reach the Frees, Mr Ornate?’ She looked up as the skipper returned with a tray on which stood an oak cafetière and some delicate rosewood cups. ‘Here you go, ma’am, here you go. I fixed it myself. You can’t trust these blankeys to fix good coffee.’ The man was blushing like a rat on a hot spot, oblivious of the open derision on Rodrigo Heat’s old-fashioned head.

Mr Oakenhurst relaxed his body and settled into his chair. Paul Minct would make his entrance at any moment.

11. LAS BON TEMPS ARRIVÉE

‘MR OAKENHURST INFORMS me that you might be willing to come in on our special play, Mrs von Bek.’ Paul Minct brushed dust from his mask. One of his pale eyes peered from the ragged hole in the Rocky Mountains where Quaker marked Colorado. It was as if he brushed a tear.

After an exhausting week-long game in which the three of them had emerged equals in all but specific skills and appetites, Paul Minct, Rose von Bek and Sam Oakenhurst believed they had learned almost everything they would ever know about one another. All were prepared, in appropriate circumstances, to risk everything on the flick of a sensor, the turn of a card, an instinctive snap judgement.

Paul Minct’s topical half-face glittered in the flamelight and behind his whispering curtain of beads his ruined lips twisted in an involuntary grin, as if flesh remembered pain his mind refused.

Sam Oakenhurst cursed his own quickened blood, the vast emotions he seemed to be riding like a vaquero on a runaway bronc, barely able to haul hard enough on the reins to avoid the worst disasters as they approached.

‘I take it you are considering some unusually high stakes, Mr Minct.’ Her voice had grown warmer, more musical, like a well practised instrument. She was all of a piece, thought Sam Oakenhurst admiringly, a perfect disguise. There was, however, no evidence that Paul Minct had been deceived by either of them.

The week’s play had left the Rose and Sam Oakenhurst uncertain lovers, but it was of no interest to Paul Minct how they celebrated their alliance. He appeared to be under the impression that a more reckless Rose von Bek had persuaded Mr Oakenhurst to let her join him.

‘Here’s my say in the matter,’ declared Sam Oakenhurst, to open the bidding. ‘Your luck and mine, Paul Minct. Even shares. Try it once? Double our luck or double our damnation, eh?’

Sam Oakenhurst knew Mr Minct viewed treachery as a legitimate instrument of policy and that nothing he offered would guarantee Mr Minct’s consistency. But he was hoping to appeal to Paul Minct’s gambler’s soul, to whet his appetite for melodrama and catch him, if possible, in a twist or two before the main game began. At present it was the only strategy he could pursue without much chance of detection.

‘You’ll stake your life on this, Mr Oakenhurst?’

‘If you’ll give us some idea of the odds and the winnings, sir.’

‘Good odds, limitless reward. My word on it. And your word, Mr Oakenhurst. How do you value it?’

‘I value my word above my life, sir. In these troubled times a jugador has nothing but honour. I will need to know a little more before I stake my honour. So I’ll fold for the moment. Save to say this, sir - you play an honest game and so will I.’

‘And you, Mrs von Bek?’ Paul Minct made an old-fashioned bow. ‘Do you also offer an honest game?’

‘I have played no other up to now, Mr Minct. I’ll throw in all I have, if the prize suits me. We can triple our luck, if you like. We all have some idea of the size of the stakes, I think. But not the size of the bonanza. Whatever it shall be, I’ll put in my full third and take out my full third - or any fraction decided by any future numbers.’

‘You can’t say fairer than that, ma’am. Very well, Mr Oakenhurst. We have another pard.’

Sam Oakenhurst could not fathom her style, but he recognized that she was a peerless mukhamir. It was as if she had trained in the very heart of Africa. She was his superior in everything but low cunning, that instinctive talent for self-preservation which had proven so useful to him and which had resulted in his becoming kin to the machinoix, rather than their prey. He had never underestimated this useful flaw in his character. But now it could only serve his honour and help him keep his word to the Rose. He had no other choice.

She had played Paul Minct well so far. Mr Minct’s weakness was that he had less respect for a woman than he had for a man. Yet the enmascaro was in no doubt about her worth to their enterprise, so long as, in his view, Mr Oakenhurst kept her under control.

‘I have always preferred the company of women,’ said Paul Minct. ‘It will be a pleasure to work with you, my dear.’

‘I like the feel of the game,’ she said. As yet she had given Sam Oakenhurst no clue as to the nature of her quarrel with Mr Minct or why the masked man did not recognize her (or did not choose to recognize her. He was the master of any five-dimensional bluff on the screen and a few more of his own invention.)

‘We shall form a family as strong as our faith in our own strengths,’ said Paul Minct. For once his eyes looked away from them, as if ashamed. ‘We are peers. We need no others. The three of us will take our sacrifice to the Fault and reap the measureless harvests!’

‘You anticipated my sentiments, Mr Minct,’ said the Rose, almost sweet, and Sam Oakenhurst thought he caught a swiftly controlled flicker of emotion in Paul Minct’s bleak eyes.

12. UN HOMME DE PITIE

THE RULES AT last agreed, Paul Minct promised to tell them more after they reached the Frees and were off the raft. Then the three of them settled down to an easy companionship, playing a hand or two of old flat and a simulated folded paper version of Henri’s Special Turbulence which could only be modified with difficulty and which they eventually abandoned by mutual consent.

One evening, as Captain Ornate pumped his melancholy squeezebox in a corner and a couple of whiteys capered to the old familiar zee tunes, the conversation turned to the subject of animals and whether it was possible to have significant communication with them.

Mrs von Bek spoke of the famous Englishman, Squire Begg, a cousin of hers, and his affinity with crows. He believed they possessed a primitive wisdom enabling them to talk in some way with humans, but first one had to learn and obey their language and customs, which were simple enough, though immutable. It was by these customs that, down the long millennia, crows survived. Assured of your courtesy, the crow would give full attention to your thoughts and desires. ‘Crows,’ she said, ‘came from all over the world to his London mansion in Sporting Club Square, and he was frequently sketched in the company of Egyptian, Amazonian or Antipodean crows, mostly hooded, who would mysteriously leave, returning without warning to their native grounds.’

‘I was once an initiate of my tribe’s Crow Cult. ‘ Rodrigo Heat’s words were thick as Mississippi mud. ‘My totem was the crow. I was sworn to protect the crow and all his kind, even with my life, even above my family. In return the crow offered us his wisdom. But his advice was not always suited to modem times.’

‘I heard of a young buckaree from up in Arizone who had his eyes pecked out by a crow. He went crazy in the sun, they said, and jumped off that old London Bridge up there, straight down until he hit the granite, thinking he was a crow,’ said Sister Honesty Marvell. ‘Nobody ever found out why.’

Sam Oakenhurst suggested a game of Mad John Parker, but Honesty Marvell favoured Doc Granite, so in the end they made it a tambourine game and shouted like kiddikins over it. That night the Rose told Sam Oakenhurst that they might have to kill Paul Minct.

At your service, he signalled, but bile came up in his throat.

(We are not fragments of the whole, she would tell him, but versions of the whole. Mr Oakenhurst had told her of the last time he had stood in a ploughed field, full of bright pools of winter rain, on a fine, pale blue evening, with the great orange sun bleeding down into the horizon, and watched a big dog fox, brush high as he picked his way amongst the furrows, circling the meadow where he was hidden by the lattice of the hedge, sniffing the wind for the geese who had begun to cluck with anxious enquiry. All of it disappeared, Mr Oakenhurst said, in the Hattiesburg Roar. ‘I had thought that, at least, must endure. Now, even our memories are becoming suspect.’)

He had no qualms about killing the man, if he proved actively dangerous to them, but he was not at all sure he could play this. He had given his word to something for which he might not possess the necessary bottom. By now he was as nervous of losing her approval as he was terrified by Paul Minct’s displeasure. The irony of this amused and sustained him.

‘Ma romance,’ she sang, ‘nouvelle romance. Ma romancier, muy necromancier. Joli boys all dansez. Joli boys all dansez. But they shall not have muy coleur.’

13. EL BUENO, EL FEO Y EL MALO

THE THREE LEFT The Whole Hog on a mudbank near Poker Flats but not before Sister Honesty Marvell had butchered Roy Ornate in a quarrel over the nature of things. Paul Minct had finished her with a glass spike whereupon the swamp people, some devolved survivalists, had tried to crawl aboard, to be repulsed and mostly blown apart by the violent anti-gravity reaction of the colour to metal. They were extinguished by the power of their ornaments. Carly O’Dowd was dead, too, from a poison she had picked up somewhere, and there was reasonable fear of a whitey uprising until Rodrigo Heat put himself in charge.

Almost as soon as they were ashore they came upon a scattering of the swamp people’s weapons, flung this far into the reed beds by the colour. Sam Oakenhurst had never held an original Olivetté PP6 before and he treasured the instrument in his hands, to the Rose’s open amusement.

‘Take up one of these weapons for yourself, ma’am.’ Paul Minct became proprietorial, motioning with his wicked fingers. ‘It will almost certainly prove useful to you.’ He bent and his arms, encased in hide, again emerged from their velvet wrappings to examine the scattered hardware. ‘I have made this journey before. Many times, this journey. Yes. This time we will go on.’ He straightened, turning the glittering weapon in her direction and, gasping at sudden pain, examined his pricked wrist. He watched the wand that had wounded him disappearing back into her cloak at the same moment as she apologized.

‘She is sometimes hasty in my defence.’

‘Swift Thom,’ he said.

The wind was ugly in their ears. A grey whine from the north.

‘You would not prefer to pack this OK9?’ continued Paul Minct. ‘Some kind of back up?’ He dangled the thing by its flared snout, as if tempting a whitey gal to a piece of pie. But she had stirred a memory in him and he turned away, looking out to where the saplings shivered. To Sam Oakenhurst she flashed a fresh play, then she gathered her gravitas so that when, also controlled, Mr Minct turned back, she seemed proudly insouciant of any slight.

Again Sam Oakenhurst recognized a game beyond his usual experience.

‘She is all I shall need,’ said the Rose, almost distantly, while Paul Minct retreated, having apologized with equal formality. He took the OK9 for himself and also hid a Ryman’s 32/80 (“a beastly, primitive weapon”) in his pack.

They were walking up a well-marked old road which followed the edge of the lake. The road had run between Shreveport and Houston once. They could follow it, Paul Minct assured them, as far as San Augustine. ‘I have heard or read of a weapon called Swift Thom,’ he added as he lengthened his gait to lead them South. ‘The subject of some epic.’

‘Not the subject,’ she said. Oh, he is easily clever enough to kill me, Sam. He tricked me into a show.

He doesn’t know that he succeeded. He will not dare risk a move on you until he’s sure of me. Sam Oakenhurst fell in beside her.

I must take risks, Sam. He must not escape me. I am pledged to his destruction.

‘Hey, hola! Les bon temps rolla! Ai, ha! The good times pass! Pauvre pierrot, muy coeur, mon beau soleil,’ sang out Paul Minct up ahead. ‘What a day, pards! What a day!’

A tremor moved the ground and the reed beds rippled.

Around them suddenly boiled the cloudy landscapes, the powerful mirages, of the Free States, all in a condition of minor agitation, as if not fully in focus. Crazy tendrils erupted into a bewildering kaleidoscope, each fragment a fresh version of its surroundings and of the people inhabiting them. A thousand images of themselves, in a variety of roles and identities, poured away down fresh cracks in the fabric of their histories.

Sam Oakenhurst found this a depressing illusion.

‘They refuse to search for the centre and hold to it against all attacks and temptations. There must be sacrifices. Lines drawn. And faith. You’re familiar with The Pilgrim’s Progress, Mr Oakenhurst, you being a preacher’s son? There’s a book, eh? But if only life were so simple. We must press on, holding together, through this valley of desolation, to our just reward. We must know complete trust. And what a reward, my dears!’

Orange and yellow pillars pissed like egg yoke into the sky and splashed upon a gory firmament.

‘Here we are,’ sang Paul Minct. ‘This is it!’ He paused before the yelling pillars and threw back his head as if to drink them up; his crude cartographic visor flickered and flashed and made new reflections. ‘We are about to pass into the Free States. This is the malleable world indeed! This, or one like it, must bend to our will. Do you not think?’

The Rose was unimpressed. Not as malleable as some, she told Sam Oakenhurst. She moved with an extra grace as if until now her blood had hardly quickened. She had the alertness of an animal in its natural element. Sam Oakenhurst thought they were walking into the suburbs of Hell and he told her that while he remained at her service he was also entirely in her hands. This experience was too unfamiliar. He had thought the stories only legends.

‘Here is what all matter should aspire to,’ Paul Minct continued. ‘Here is true tolerance. Everything is free.’

‘Tolerance without mercy,’ murmured Sam Oakenhurst, willing to reveal this fear if only to disguise his other, more profound, anxieties.

‘We shall find further allies here!’ Paul Minct appeared to have forgotten his earlier pledge as he led them between the columns. ‘I will guide you.’

But it was soon left for the Rose to lead them, with miraculous confidence, through the vivid shadows, through volatile matter and corrupted time. Perspective, gravity and the seasons were all unstable and Sam Oakenhurst felt he must throw up as Paul Minct, with angry gestures of refusal, had done after they had walked the Bridge of Rubies for uncountable hours. Mr Minct, expecting to be the most experienced of them, clearly resented the Rose’s easy pathfinding. Generally he managed to hide his feelings. It was as if, with the sureness of one who knew such waters well, she steered their boat through the wildest rapids.

Agitated scratchings came from within Paul Minct’s mask and swaddlings. Occasionally the enmascaro uttered a little, shrill bubbling sound which added to Sam Oakenhurst’s own fearful nausea. For a while it seemed they passed between fields of stars, crossing by silver spans of moonbeams, but the Rose told them it was the abandoned forecourt of The Divided Arabia which at one time had been the largest shopping mall in the Western Hemisphere. What they witnessed was what it had become.

‘That stuff scares the devil out of me,’ Sam Oakenhurst admitted as they emerged from a forest of bright metallic greenery into a wide relief of desert dominated by the brazen stability of a tiny sun.

‘Now, my dears, this is more like Texas,’ said Paul Minct.

14. NO ME ENTIERRES EN LA PRADERA

THE FIRST TOWN they reached was Poker Flats, built in a wide yellow plain in what had been, Paul Minct told them, the old mustard-growing region. Her streets were full of whiteys and mixed couples and she was clearly a town given over almost entirely to license. Poker Flats announced herself as the Theater Capital of the Southwest and her main boardwalk was nothing but vivid marquees and billboards advertising simulatings, using living actors, of the great local V heroes, whose adventures Sam Oakenhurst had already skimmed at Lieutenant Twist’s. These were elaborate dramas concerning the love triangle of Pearl Peru, Bullybop and Fearless Frank Force, or the Quest for the Fishlings, featuring Professor Pop, Captain Billy Bob Begg and her Famous Chaos Engineers. Many of the protagonists were white. White barkers stood outside their booths and called to the newcomers. ‘So true you’d think it was V! Dallas Horizon.’ / ’It’s the net! Ontario Outer.’ / ‘Virtually V! Laramee Deadlock.’ / ‘Frank Force Face To Face! Ludoland.’ Their words were echoed overhead in the baroque calligraphy of the day. Power paint growled with all the brilliant vulgar bellicosity of the old circus towns. Poker Flats had been the first of the roving show cities to take permanent root. Such settlements were all over the Free States now, said Paul Minct, but the biggest were still Poker Flats and Porto Cristo.

Paul Minct insisted they visit the shows and understand the nature of these dramas. ‘Real or fictional, black or white, they represent a breed of our own kind that has successfully escaped the logic of the Fault, discovering new universes beyond our own. There, my dear friends, Chaos and Singularity perpetually war, are perpetually in balance. And sometimes one is no longer certain which is which. Philosophies become blurred and intermingled out there in the Second Ether. This was how I first learned that it was possible to move from one version of our universe to another and survive. We never die, my dear friends. We are, however, perpetually translated.’

What does he mean? asked Sam Oakenhurst.

He understands something of our condition, she told him, but not much of it. He is like those old South American conquistadori. All he can see of this secret is the power and wealth it will bring him. He is prepared to risk his life and soul for that.

Sam Oakenhurst grew fascinated with the legends portrayed on the stages. He talked about Pearl Peru, Corporal Pork, Little Rupoldo, Kapricom Schultz and others as if they were personally known to him. When the time came to leave Poker Flats, he bought several books of scenarios. As soon as they were back on the trail he studied them slowly, from morning to night, hoping to find clues to the versions of reality perceived both by Paul Minct and, in particular, Mrs von Bek. Perhaps the Fault was not the mouth of Hell, after all? Perhaps it was a gateway to Paradise?

Walking beside the Rose, he recounted the tale of Oxford under the Squad warlords. The alien renegades, furious at Oxford’s resistance to their philosophies, informed the citizens that unless they immediately fell to levelling their entire settlement, colleges, chapels and all, they (the Squads) would eat their first born and bugger their old folk. ‘And Oxford, Rose, went the way of St Petersburg and Washington, but not Cheltenham, which is still standing but which has lost its first born. And her old people rarely, these days, walk abroad. ‘ The Squads had come in their black deltoid aircraft. Thousands. ‘They told us they represented the Singularity and we were now their subject race. If we refused to serve them, they punished us until we accepted their mastery. They have conquered, they boast, half the known multiverse and are destined to conquer the rest. Fearless Frank Force is their greatest ace. But nobody knows or understands the loyalties of the Merchant Venturer, Pearl Peru, whom he loves to distraction. His love is not returned. Pearl’s passion is for Bullybop alone. And Bullybop is a thorn in the side of the Singularity. Nobody is sure of her secret identity. Honour demands that Frank Force issue no challenge to his rival, yet Bullybop is marked by the Singularity as an outlaw. Here now is the moral conundrum we must solve before we can proceed along a further branch. There is a road, after all, Rose. There are many roads. And crossroads. I can sense them. We can choose some which exist or we can create our own. But there’s a formula, I know, and I must learn it.’

‘This mania came over one of my men the first time we ever passed through Poker Flats.’ Paul Minct was cheerfully dismissive of the Rose’s fears. ‘They either recover or they don’t. In the end we had to shoot Peter Agoubi, poor chap. Lead on, Mrs von Bek. I’ll take care of Mr Oakenhurst.’

‘It will pass,’ she said. ‘He will regain control of himself soon, I am sure.’ For my sake, Sam, if not your own!

This demand brought him, within a reasonable period, back to his senses, but his lasting emotion was of loss, as if he had been close to the secret logic of the multiverse and able, like her, to navigate a purposeful course through those quasi-realities. He could not make himself throw away his scenarios. He buried them deep at the bottom of his knapsack.

‘It’s unflattering to have a V character for a rival,’ she pretended amusement. They had found some good beds in a ghost town about a hundred kays from San Augustine. She indulged her weariness, her poor temper. ‘What is the actuality of this Pearl Peru? She sailed by accident through the Cloud of Saffron and that made her a heroine?’

In any circumstances Sam Oakenhurst would have decided that it was impolitic to show admiration for a character with whom the Rose seemed to be on intimate terms and whom she disliked. Such experiences were not, he told himself, helping his sense of identity. Once he caught himself yearning for the familiarity of the machinoix shutterbox.

Those people were real, he knew. But what he had experienced as myth, she had experienced as history. He vowed that he must never lose her. He was prepared to change most of his life for her. His curiosity about her was as great as his love. Now, he thought, they are impossible to separate. Our shoots are interwound. Our luck is the same. We are of the Just... He had a moment’s understanding that he had given up his own madness in favour of hers. What had he accepted?

You are sworn to this, she reminded him. From now you must accept only what I determine as the truth. You will survive no other way. Any independent decision of yours could result in my death. You know this, Sam. You have dealt the hands. Now you must play the game, or we are both dead.

This is new to me, he said.

Play it anyway.

15. TWO STEP DELLA TEXAS

AFTER THEY HAD traded the Ryman’s and two samsonites for ponies at the Flooding Whisper horse ranch just west of San Augustine they made better progress into Golden Birches, where pale light shuddered and huge crows flapped amongst the black lattice of the distant treetops. They arrived in Lufkin to discover that the Pennsylvania Rooms were still run by Major Moyra Malu, the shade of an elegant old swashbuckler who had fought with K’Ond’aa Taylor at Pampam Ridge and had carried the flag to victory for Charles Deslondes in ‘07.

At Paul Minct’s suggestion she was to be their fourth, but not before another week’s gaming had all parties apparently satisfied. Then they took Major Moyra’s good Arabs and headed through the milk tides down to Livingston where Paul Minct sought out Herb Frazee. The ex-president of the Republic was giving demonstration hands of Cold Annie and telling Tarot to what was left of Livingston’s polite society. He refused Mr Minct’s invitation but suggested they look up Mrs Sally Guand’ in Houston.

The road to Houston took them through Silver Pines. The strange, frozen forest was cold as death nowadays, said Paul Minct, but once there had been fires burning on every mound. They came out into foothills above a summer valley. ‘There’s Houston.’ Paul Minct pointed. The huge city had recently melted and reformed into a baroque version of itself. Its highways made arabesques, glorious in the sunlight. Yet even here the uneasy terrain threatened to vaporize, become something else, and Sam Oakenhurst yearned for California where Pearl Peru, he had read, was a living celebrity.

They passed under Houston’s organic freeways. The Rose wanted to stay for a few days. The others insisted they find Sally Guand’ and press on to Galveston. But when Major Moyra Malu led them to Sally Guand’s old offices above the Union Station, the buildings were melted shells and the rails had twisted themselves into one vast, elongated abstract sculpture disappearing in the direction of Los Angeles. Here, as everywhere, black and white lived as best they could, equals amongst the ruins, and miscegeny was not uncommon.

They lost the road some twenty kays from Houston, used up their provisions and were forced to shoot a horse before they got on another trace full of abandoned buses and pickup trucks, which took them across to Old Galveston to find Jasmine Shah, who had been operating a bar on the harbourfront until the local vigilantes busted her huge cache of piles noires. Her dark locks hiding a long, vulpine face, she was ready, she said, to do almost anything, yet she would only come in with them after she had whispered strict conditions to each one in private. She revealed that she, like Major Moyra, was now a shade.

Paul Minct had hesitated after she spoke to him, but then he nodded agreement.

The streets of Galveston were full of whiteys who had failed to fulfil the ambitions they had conceived in Mississippi and Alabama and were now desperately trying to get back to New Orleans, but could not afford any kind of fare. Black travellers were beset by scores of them whining for help.

Sam Oakenhurst was glad when they got aboard the first schoomer available and sailed out into the peaceful waters of the Gulf. He and the Rose now had a better measure of the situation and yet he no longer had faith in his own good judgement. The thought of New Orleans was already beginning to obsess him.

The Rose begged him to rally. ‘It seems Mr Minct does intend to sail into the Fault. Yet why would he insist on your finding us a meat boat?’ (Paul Minct had commissioned Sam Oakenhurst to approach the machinoix.) ‘Does he want us alive when he goes in?’ Both agreed that Paul Minct had needed more partners only after Swift Thom had stirred some memory. ‘How does he plan to kill us?’ Sam wondered. ‘Perhaps he will not kill me until he has made sure of you, Rose. And you are necessary to him, I think. He knows you can help him.’

‘But you, too, are necessary if he is to get the meat boat. You heard him insist. It must only be a meat boat. Has anyone ever volunteered to sail on such a boat?’

‘It is forbidden,’ said Sam Oakenhurst. ‘He knows it is.’

‘Then he demands of you a complex betrayal. Is this how he would weaken us?’ The Rose began to brush her exquisite hair. ‘Who would you betray?’

‘Not you,’ he said. ‘Not myself. Nothing I value.’

‘Betray the machinoix and surely you betray yourself. You have explained all this to me. And in betraying yourself you must betray me. How will you resolve this? It is a problem worthy of Fearless Frank Force.’

She seemed to be mocking him.

‘A moral conundrum,’ she added.

There was a knock on their cabin door: A kiddikin bringing Mr Minct’s compliments and looking forward to the pleasure of their company in a game of Anvils and Pins.

‘I have earned your sarcasm, I know,’ Sam Oakenhurst said. ‘But I am still willing to learn from you. What will you teach me, Rose?’

‘You will learn that it is, space and time, always a question of scale.’ She touched his lips. ‘Meanwhile you must continue to risk your life. And you are sworn to serve me, are you not?’

‘On my honour,’ he said.

‘But in demanding your help I expose you to more than you ever expected,’ she said. ‘Perhaps you do not have the resources?’

‘I have them,’ he insisted.

‘You must draw upon your archetype.’ The Rose took his hand. Tonight her skin resembled fine, delicately shaded petals softly layered upon her sturdy frame. ‘I have lost my home and must destroy the man who robbed me of it. We are only barely related as species, you and I, but it is Time and Scale which separate us, Sam. In the ether we embrace metamorphosis. You and I, Sam, understand the dominating law of the multiverse. We are ruled by multiplying chance. But we need not be controlled by it. I knew Paul Minct in another guise. Now, I think, he clearly remembers me. He can always recall a weapon, that one, if not a woman. This pair, these shadows, are an afterthought. His interest in the Fault could be secondary now. First he must deal with us, for we threaten his existence. Perhaps he is afraid to let us reach the Fault with him, lest he be cheated of whatever it is he has schemed for? Believe me, Sam, Paul Minct will be giving us his full attention for the next few days. These others, they are scarcely real, merely 1st and 2nd Murderers.’

16. J’AI PASSE DEVANTTA PORTE

THE MACHINOIX HAD sniffed his coming. Sam Oakenhurst stood at the rail of the great triple-hulled schoomer and saw through Major Moyra’s glass that his brothers and sisters had assembled to greet him.

Their snorting, half-organic vehicles, dark green and brown with senility, drooled and defecated on the quayside while neither citizen nor armed militia dare show disgust or objection. In their city, the machinoix were ignored for the same reason quakes were ignored in Los Angeles. They were unavoidable and unpredictable.

Mr Sam Oakenhurst tasted their power as greedily as he embraced their kinship. His veins thrilled with the memory of his long courtships under the shutterbox, his lingering initiations, his education in seduction. Beware, he signalled the Rose, for I am enraptured already. I love you, Rose. Only you.

The Rose held fast to him and gave him the strength she could spare. He knew there was no physical danger. Any decision of his would be accepted, for he threatened nothing the machinoix valued. This knowledge was insufficient to steady his nerve. He had to call on his every resource and never reveal a hint of his condition to Paul Minct and his colleagues. The Rose, understanding the importance of this deception to her own interests, gave him more support. She had no choice. He was her only ally and while he lived so did she. And she loved him, she said.

By the time they had clambered down the gangway to the lighter, he was scarcely able to disguise the signs of his massive emotional conflict.

With her help, however, he succeeded. He at last stood four square on the quayside, clutching her arm once before advancing towards the middle vehicle from which oddly tattooed hands beckoned, their fingers fractured and re-set at peculiar angles with inserted precious stones and gold. Gnarled as old hedges, the hands had the appearance of eccentrically made robot digits, jointed and decorated for their beauty rather than their function.

The Rose was casual enough as she turned to inform a nervous Mr Minct that Sam Oakenhurst spoke machinoix perfectly. ‘He is the only possible interpreter. He will get us swift passage to Biloxi’

‘It must be the meat boat.’ Paul Minct was wheezing from his recent climb up the iron waterstair. ‘I know they reserve it for themselves but it is what we must have.’

By arrangement with the ship’s captain they were to stay in Rue Dauphine at the Hotel Audobon, a collection of old iron slave shacks turned into elegant cabines à la mode. The uniformed whiteys who greeted them at the gates were not permitted to take the little luggage the gamblers brought.

These were cabins of choice, let only to passing visitors of their own high persuasion. When they were settled, Paul Minct told them, they must assemble at Brown’s Bar Vieux on Royale, where he would hire the backroom and a couple of simul-bottles. They could thus link up for a rough and ready run-through of their plan to enter the Fault aboard the meat boat. ‘We’ll be going in through Mustard Splash or Ketchup Cave.’

The bottles were the best quality the Rose had ever seen. Major Moyra and Jasmine Shah were experts at handling and conducting them, massaging unstable gases, nursing their milky energy into responsive motes.

Before they had arrived, Paul Minct had refused to tell her why they must go to this trouble when the Terminal’s huge V resource was at anyone’s disposal. He appeared to have reasons for not alerting the people at the Terminal to his intentions.

Her instincts told her that this whole charade was part of a complicated plot to trap her before killing her. It was unnecessarily elaborate, she thought.

But it was that which convinced her. Elaboration was Paul Minct’s trademark. It was characteristic of his whole game thus to hide a simple brute intention.

Had he known she was in Guadalajara? If so, even Paul Minct’s affectation for M&E was a part of his plot against her. She was admiring of his mind for detail. She had known him in many roles, but usually he had not recognized her so quickly.

When Mr Oakenhurst rejoined them at Brown’s he seemed introspective but carefree enough, almost euphoric. He told them that they had the machinoix blessing to take the meat boat to Biloxi. This was, they must all understand, a considerable privilege. Moyra Malu said she appreciated the implications. Only Paul Minct accepted the news casually, as if Mr Oakenhurst had done no more than act as a go-between. ‘And how much do these great barons charge us, Mr Oakenhurst, for the privilege?’

‘Nothing, Mr Minct. They act upon my word alone.’

‘Flimsy enough, then?’

Sam Oakenhurst took a glaring interest in the screens, his mood threatening.

‘I am not sure I can stand that smell for such a long voyage,’ said Jasmine Shah. She had changed to red satin, she said, in honour of the occasion. She sported a feathery fan.

‘We must endure it until Biloxi,’ murmured Paul Minct, looking up from the bottles and retorts of his quasi-V, his mask reflecting the brilliant, ever-changing rhythms of the angry pastels. ‘They are unpredictable, are they not, sir, these psychics? Sometimes they seem to need us more than we need them. But I expect they are agreeable people, by and large.’

Sam Oakenhurst knew he had nothing much more to fear until they were actually aboard the meat boat. He took his place with the other four around the viewing bowls which flooded them now in bright blues and vivid pinks, adjusting to a formal plum colour as Paul Minct stroked his backupper to make shapes from the enlivened dust. Some of the images were familiar but many were not. Sam Oakenhurst found them obscene.

‘We have agreed a common principle, my dears,’ Paul Minct seemed a little sanctimonious. ‘And must stick to the rules we form here tonight. Or we shall be lost.’

‘Do we need to be reminded of that?’ Sam Oakenhurst was almost irritable as he studied the bowl, finding some strands on the screen he could use. He wove a showy, challenging pattern.

‘We are a team, Mr Oakenhurst.’ Paul Minct seemed pleased by this offhand display. ‘We can afford no weak links. No, as it were, anti-socialism.’ Sam Oakenhurst guessed Mr Minct had found a tune which he must now rehearse for a while. Mr Minct searched under his veil and plucked at his hideous jowls.

Unusually alert, Sam Oakenhurst studied Paul Minct’s companions and detected a tremor of victorious malice in Major Moyra’s face. The Rose’s warning was confirmed. Certain of his allies, Paul Minct was celebrating a premature triumph.

It will be on board the meat boat. That has always featured in his scenario, I think. I don’t know why, save that he follows a personal aesthetic. Mrs von Bek gave her own attention to the bowls and began a detailed weaving, a story of a planet and its doom, a wonderful miniature. Sam Oakenhurst understood that now she, too, had issued a challenge to Paul Minct. These were the gentle beginnings, the courteous preliminaries of the game.

Upon Mr Minct’s irrational insistence they began the first stage of their simulation, producing a reasonable version of the Biloxi Fault and some sort of boat in which to brave these self-created dangers. ‘Now we sail into Mustard Splash!’ declared Paul Minct, their captain. ‘These murky walls will part, thus!’ A magician, he revealed the blinding azure of a vast colour field. ‘We shall follow a river - thus –-’  A hazier network of silver streams which, with his characteristic crudity, he made into one wide road. ‘This line will respond to the meat boat’s unique geometry. And now we must do our best, dear friends, and make the most of our creative imaginations, for our quest lies even beyond the fields of colour - to find eternal life, limitless wealth! There one shall come in to one’s true power at last!’

~ * ~

Later, in their cabin, Sam Oakenhurst and the Rose agreed that the exercise had been a complicated sham, a violent and exhausting process with no other purpose, as far as they could tell, than to display Paul Minct’s artistic skills. ‘That was not the Fault,’ she said. ‘Merely a surface impression and a bad projection. It was an arcadium, no more. Almost an insult. I wonder why? To convince us? To confuse us? To terrify us? He knows in his heart what truly lies beyond the Fault.’

They were lying together on the wide bed, the light from the swamp-cone turning her brown skin into semi-stable green and giving her face a deep flush. ‘He still needs our good will, Sam. He had expected your challenge no more than had I.’

It had hardly been a challenge. Mr Oakenhurst, hyped on the sensations of his reunion, had merely wished to show that he no longer feared Paul Minct. He had risked their lives on a vulgar display and he now admitted it.

She began to laugh with quiet spontaneity. ‘I have a feeling he did not care to notice, anyway. He was preparing his talents for his demo. Let that hand ride for a while, Sam, and we’ll see what happens.’

He marvelled at her beauty, the peerless texture of her skin, her natural, sweet scent, the ever-changing colours of her flesh, and he knew that his feeling for her was stronger than his bond with the machinoix. Stronger than with his own species.

‘We are defenceless if he decides to take us before the meat boat leaves,’ he said. ‘I’m pretty scared, Rose.’

‘The best way to get out of trouble is to take a risk based on your judgement. You know that, Sam.’ Her touch was a petal on his thigh. ‘Take another risk. An informed one, this time. Make a change. What can you ever lose? Not me, Sam.’

She began to notice the tiny, symmetrical marks on his stomach, like stylized drops of blood.

He refused to tell her what they were.

17. EXITOSDEORO

THE MEAT BOAT left two days later from the quarantine dock, its brooding, over-decorated reptilian bulk almost filling the ancient channel. It was lying low in the water, giving the impression that it had just fed well.

In common with the others, Paul Minct had to steady himself against the smell from the holds. He held a huge nosegay of mint and rosemary to his hidden features, while the strength of the perfume sprayed about by Major Moyra was equally hard to stomach. Jasmine Shah contented herself with her fan and some smelling salts. She seemed lost in her own small fantasy.

They were led aboard by an obsequious whitey tattooed with the machinoix livery. The extravagantly furnished passenger quarters were clearly designed for the unwholesome comforts of the machinoix. It was a great honour, Sam Oakenhurst told them. The majority of quarters reserved for the machinoix were less comfortable. And there were quarters for the blankey slaves much closer to the meat.

He and the Rose stood together in the centre of Paul Minct’s cabin while the huge creature prowled about the edges, the nosegay still pressed to his beaded veil, inspecting the peculiar cups and little needles placed everywhere for a guest’s casual convenience. Sam Oakenhurst reached down to atiny table and picked up one of the razor-edged shot glasses. He gently touched it to the back of his wrist.

‘These colours are so muted,’ declared the Rose. ‘So gorgeous. So rich.’

‘There’s no-one doubts the machinoix ain’t rich, Mrs von Bek,’ chuckled Jasmine Shah, crowding in with Major Moyra to admire the vast chamber. ‘As Croesus, they say.’

‘Could buy and sell the Republic of Texas, even in my day,’ Major Moyra agreed. ‘But they don’t mess with human politics much. Ain’t that so, Mr Oakenhurst?’

‘That’s so, major.’

‘Built for a giant and furnished for dwarves,’ mused Jasmine Shah, making her own tour.

The atmosphere was one of general bonhomie as the would-be murderers saw their end-game laid out, already won.

Their adversaries’ confidence could be useful to them, Sam Oakenhurst decided, and later in their own cabin, Rose von Bek told him she had decided the same. ‘Their eagerness and anticipation can become our weapon. But it is three days to Biloxi. When will he strike, do you think?’

Sam Oakenhurst made a lazy gesture. He thought it would not be immediately. For the first time he was calmly ready for death. He did not much care how he died. He also knew that he could not accept death while his obligation to the Rose remained. He must make himself worthy of her.

She detected a certain heaviness in his manner. He assured her that he had never been on better form.

While a blankey, smelling strongly of meat, prepared their bed, Sam Oakenhurst said aloud: ‘If Paul Minct hopes to seduce whiteys to his cause he cannot know the machinoix. This fellow and his kind are as loyal to their masters as anyone can be. Disobedience or treachery is inconceivable to them. They would be disgusted and terrified if it was suggested. The machinoix never put their own to work on the meat boats. They trust their whiteys absolutely. There is no reason why they should not.’

‘Paul Minct must have some understanding of this. How does he think he can force them to divert the boat and sail into the Fault?’ The Rose shook her head.

‘Whether or not he plans to enter the Fault, he is without a doubt planning to trap us. He cannot see how we can escape and is happy to take his time. Yet why should he go to such lengths to kill you, Rose?’

‘He must be certain. And it is in his nature to make such plots. He knows that I have pursued him through the myriad branches of the multi verse and that I am of the Just. I must put an end to him, if I can. Betrayal is a sophisticated and legitimate art which he practises merely for the pleasure it gives him. But he has another ambition I cannot fathom, as yet.’

‘What did he do to you that you must punish him?’ Sam Oakenhurst asked.

‘He educated me to betray myself and thus to betray my people. ‘ She spoke softly, economically, as if she could not trust her voice for long. ‘The story I gave at Brown’s was true.’

‘And these other stories? Are they true? What we saw at Poker Flats?’

‘Myths,’ she said. ‘True enough. They describe the truth.’

‘And what does Paul Minct describe?’

‘Only lies, Sam.’

With hideous dignity the whitey bowed and left the cabin.

18. MON BON VIEUX MARI

‘WE WERE CALLED the daughters of the Garden, the daughters of the Just,’ she told him. ‘We reproduced ourselves by the occasional effort of will. We understood the principles of self-similarity. I suppose you would call it an instinct. There is no particular miracle in being, as we were, part flora, part mammal. Such syntheses are common to the worlds I usually inhabit. Paul Minct made me cross so many scales and forget so many lives to reach him. The stories are always a little different. But this time, I think, we shall achieve some kind of resolution.’

‘Surely, we are something more than mere echoes... ?’ Yet even as he said this Sam Oakenhurst felt oppression lifting from him and a rare peace replacing it. In combination with what the machinoix had given him, he found still more strength. He had reached a kind of equilibrium. At that moment nothing was puzzling. But was this merely an illusion of control? What she had told him should have dismayed him. Had her madness completely absorbed him?

‘Our science was the science of equity,’ she continued. ‘We were the natural enemies of all tyrannies, no matter how well disguised. Our world occupied a universe of flowers; blossoms and leaves were woven between blooms the size of planets. Paul Minct allied himself with a devolved race whom we knew as Babbyboys and these he ultimately unleashed upon our world. Just before he committed that crime he was lover and I taught him all our secrets.’

‘And your sisters?’

‘Our whole universe was raped. I am the last of it.’

Until then Sam Oakenhurst had been unable to imagine a burden greater than his own.

19. DANS LE COEUR DE LA VILLE

‘WE ARE PLAYING charades, do you see!’ Paul Minct’s mask glittered with a kind of merriment. ‘Major Moyra is in the part of Little Fanny Fun, while Manly Mark Male is played by our own dashing Jasmine Shah! But who shall play the rival? Who shall play Handsome Harry Ho-Ho? You know this one, Mr Oakenhurst, I’m sure.’

‘Those tales no longer fascinate me, Mr Minct.’ Sam Oakenhurst stood just within the cabin door. The three would-be murderers had pushed away furniture and draperies and made a stage of a broad, ebony table, its legs carved with a catalogue of machinoix delights. It was on this that the two performed, while their superior applauded from an asymmetrical couch he had made comfortable with the sanctuary’s afterlife cushions.

‘This is disrespectful to your hosts.’

‘Oh, Mr Oakenhurst, we shall not be going back to New Orleans! We’re on our way to the Fault to find the Holy Grail, remember?’ Major Moyra bawled in open contempt and unhitched her gaudy skirts.

The Rose stepped up, anxious to end this. ‘Crude entertainment for a mind such as yours, Paul Minct. Or is this merely a leitmotif ?’

‘You are too judgemental, Mrs von Bek.’ Paul Minct turned his glaring mask this way and that as if he could barely see through the holes. ‘You must be more flexible. Only flexibility will enable you to survive the perils of the Fault. Come now, join our little time-passer. Choose a character of your own. Pearl Peru? The Spammer Gain? Corporal Pork? Karl Kapital?’

‘I have nothing further to take from this,’ said Sam Oakenhurst. ‘And nothing to put in. Play on, pards, and don’t mind me.’

‘Play for the hell of it, then!’ Jasmine Shah sprawled her painted legs over the table. ‘Play. Play. What else is there to do, Mr Oakenhurst?’ Her yellow eyes were sluggish with guilty appetites. His anticipated death was making her salivate. ‘Taste something fresh.’

The killing ritual was beginning. And so they sat obediently until they were called and Mr Oakenhurst was a somewhat wooden Harry Ho-Ho, while the Rose became Pearl Peru to the life, telling the first tale of The Spammer Gain and how her fishlings were stolen. Enough to distract Paul Minct a little and make him clap his pale hands together. ‘You are a natural actress, Mrs von Bek. You missed your vocation.

‘I think not,’ she said.

‘There, pards, we’ve proved ourselves easy sports,’ announced Sam Oakenhurst, ‘but now we must come to business. We are here to discuss the part of our plan where we take over the meat boat. Are the whiteys bribed, yet?’ Mr Oakenhurst found himself again speaking from impulse. His tone was sufficient to let the enmascaro know that Sam Oakenhurst was making a call.

‘Not yet,’ said Paul Minct easily. ‘There’s time enough, Mr Oakenhurst. Let us relax.’

‘We no longer accept you as our director.’ The Rose swung down from the table as Paul Minct, gloating in a supposed small victory, displayed his surprise. But he recovered quickly.

‘Here’s a better game than I anticipated.’ Mr Minct calmed his two shadows with a casual hand. They were both thoroughly alarmed. Evidently they had not once considered a play made at the opponents’ convenience.

Caged light, fluttering in the woven flambeaux, cast the only movement on Mr Minct now. His body was still as stone. As if he hoped to stop time.

‘This is not like you, Mr Oakenhurst.’ The Rose was amused.

‘Not like me at all.’ He turned to address the enmascaro. ‘A surprise play, eh, Mr Minct?’

Eyes moved like quick reptiles behind the mask. The curtain over the mouth rattled. ‘Just so, Mr Oakenhurst.’

Sam Oakenhurst hardly knew what to do next. He felt a rush of elation. He was in control of his terrors.

20. AIMER ET PERDRE

IT HAD NEVER been in Sam Oakenhurst’s nature to decide the first move. Paul Minct had relied on that while certain the Rose would not make a play before Mr Oakenhurst. But now, equally unpredictable, Paul Minct produced the little OK9 he had once recommended to Mrs von Bek and he took a step back to cover them both. ‘This is not my style, either, as you know. But I’m willing to change if you are. That’s the basis of a relationship, as I tell my wife. No wands now, Mrs von Bek. This beam is wide and I will resort to brute murder if I must. I have a vocation to fulfil. An oath.’

‘Ah!’ exclaimed the Rose in surprise. ‘This one has a conscience!’

‘I had such hopes for your death, Mrs von Bek. Mr Oakenhurst would have appreciated what I made of you. We have a little time before we prepare the sacrifice. Not much, but we must make the best of what God sends us.’ He signalled to Major Moyra and Jasmine Shah. Then suddenly he was still again, as if stabbed.

‘That is the one,’ said Sam Oakenhurst to the machinoix. ‘He is not my friend.’ He watched incuriously as one oddly jointed jewelled hand closed over Paul Minct’s wrist and squeezed the gun free while fingers felt through the beads deep into his mouth and throat.

Rose von Bek looked away from Paul Minct and, with Swift Thom, brought Major Moyra and Jasmine Shah merciful deaths. In the last moments the game had been unpleasantly easy as often happens in a spontaneous end-move. When the Rose looked back she saw that Paul Minct had been returned to his seat. He was not dead, but his cold eyes begged for her mercy. The rest of him had been expertly snapped here and there. He was little more than a heap of broken bones but he would live indefinitely.

Mr Oakenhurst bowed low before his invisible kin.

The voice which came from the folds of drapery behind the table was musical but oddly diffident. ‘We shall put those two with the other meat.’ There was a long pause, then: ‘The broken one is yours, if you wish.’

‘Thank you,’ said the Rose.

‘No thankings, no,’ said the machinoix. ‘Not need. I am the same. Same. You. You.’ In the following silence the Rose said: ‘Where has she gone?’

‘To rest,’ Sam Oakenhurst told her. ‘She has used up pretty much all her strength for a year. What will you do with him?’

‘Eventually I must kill him. I have that much compassion left. But it will take me a while to find the necessary resolution.’

Sam Oakenhurst stepped aside to let the whiteys drag the corpses off. ‘Nature resists linearity. Why didn’t you understand that, Paul Minct? What was your plan? What did you intend to sacrifice and to whom?’ Approaching the couch he reached to Paul Minct’s head and touched it in a certain way, allowing the lips to move.

‘The meat was for the Fault.’ His suffering made Paul Minct obedient now. ‘The Fault is a sentient creature. Five times I fed it. This sixth time was to bring me my reward, for I would be sacrificing the Rose, my mortal enemy, body and soul! And what rarer sacrifice? For the Rose is both the last and the first of her kind. Then I should have been permitted to sail through the golden branches into the Great Cup and know my whole power!’

‘You must tell me the truth,’ she said. ‘It will make me more merciful. How did you plan to take over this boat?’

‘I placed no faith in bribes or whitey revolt. I simply made adjustments to the steering gear. That is why this boat is now on inevitable course for the Fault, under full sail. We shall keep our original bargain, ma’am. But you never did confront me, Sam. Not really.’

Mr Oakenhurst silenced Paul Minct’s mouth. The man’s bravery was more impressive than his judgement. ‘We are to be your sacrifices, still? I think not. Eh, Mrs von Bek?’

The Rose frowned at him. ‘It is either the Fault or drown. Have you no curiosity, Sam?’

‘There are innocent lives in this!’

‘They will not die, Sam. That’s merely a conception of the Singularity. You have already discovered the benefits of mutability. The Fault will either translate us or reject us, but it will not kill us. And there’s every chance we’ll remain together. We must have the will for it and the courage to follow our instincts.’

‘I must return to New Orleans,’ said Mr Oakenhurst. ‘There is a debt outstanding.’ He looked with hatred into Paul Minct’s agonized eyes.

Again, he began to doubt his judgement. What good had his decisions been now they were heading helplessly into the Biloxi Fault? He turned to ask her how much time she thought they had, when the whitey bos’un shuffled down the companionway and crossed to the door, kneeling with bowed head before Sam Oakenhurst and the Rose and not speaking until Mr Oakenhurst gave permission.

‘Respectfully, master, our meat boat is about to be a-swallered by the Biloxi Fault.’

~ * ~

‘Remember!’ she called, as she followed him up the narrow ladders towards the bridge, ‘It is only a matter of scale and experience. You are not a fraction of the whole. You are a version of the whole! Time will seem to eddy and stall. This is scale. Everything is sentient, but scale alters perception. The time of a tree is not your time.’ It was as if she shouted to him all she had meant to teach him before this moment. ‘To the snail the foot which comes from nowhere and crushes him is as natural a disaster as a hurricane and as impossible to anticipate. The time of a star is not our time. Equity is the natural condition of the multiverse. There are things to fear in the colour fields, but not the fields themselves!’

Now he was on the top deck, heading for the bridge, the vast black sails bulging overhead as the freak wind took them more rapidly towards the Fault than ever Paul Minct had planned. The massive presence of the Biloxi Fault filled their horizon, all bruised colours and sharded light, yelping and gulping the ruins of star systems and galaxies as the meat boat sailed inexorably towards the lava-red glow of Ketchup Cave.

‘I will remember all your lessons!’ He took the wheel from the terrified whitey, but it would not respond to his straining movements. The boat dipped and rose on a sudden tide while the wind threatened to tear the sheets from her masts. ‘Help me,’ he said, as the whitey ran below. She came towards him. Then something soft had batted the meat boat into the middle of the bloody blossoming field. Yet the vessel maintained her original momentum, travelling steadily under sail. They could see nothing but the surrounding scarlet. When they spoke their voices were unfamiliar and used new but coherent languages. Sam Oakenhurst felt his stomach peeling open, his entire flesh and bones skinless to the flame. He fell backwards.

He tried to look up beyond the sails and saw something moving against the scarlet. A huge owl. He shuddered.

Now the Rose had her hands upon the useless wheel. Mammalian only in broad outline, she appeared to curl her limbs and cast roots into the steering machinery, as if seeking the whereabouts of Paul Minct’s tamperings. Her scent enraptured him. It was thicker than smoke. Something vicious and insistent threatened nearby and was dangerous, some version of Paul Minct. The Rose pulled mightily on the wheel and this time the meat boat responded, gliding into a sudden field of blue populated with the black silhouettes of mountains shifting constantly in perspective, and then descending into a maelstrom of purple and white, soaring into field upon field of the vast spectrum, turning and wheeling until Sam Oakenhurst had to take his eyes from her to lean over the side and throw up into an infinity of lemon yellow spheres and witness his own vomit becoming another universe in which uncountable souls would live, suffer and die until the end of time, while the sounds that he made would eventually be interpreted by them as evidence of a Guiding Principle.

The Rose was laughing. Sam Oakenhurst had never seen a creature so filled with joy, with the rage of risk and skill which marked the greatest jugaderos. He had never known a creature so daring, so wise. And it seemed to him that some new strength bound him to her, through all the colour-flooded fields of the multiverse. And then she began to sing.

The beauty of her song was almost unbearable. He began to weep and his tears were blinding quicksilver. It was as if she had summoned a wind and the wind was her voice calling to him.

‘Look up, Sam! There, beyond the colour fields! It’s the Grail, Sam. It’s the great Grail itself!’

But when his eyes were clear of tears Sam Oakenhurst looked up and all he saw was a lattice of light, like roots and branches, twisting around them on every side, a kind of nest made of curled gold and silver rays. And through this, with happy ease, the Rose steered the machinoix meat boat. Her hair was wild around her head, like flames; her limbs a haze of petals and brambles; and her song seemed to fill the multiverse.

The meat boat was a fat brazen lizard crawling over the surfaces of the vast fields, following the complex river systems which united them, replenished them, blending with new multihued mercury fractures running through a million dimensions and remaking themselves, fold upon fold, scale upon scale, until they merged again with the great main trunks, ancient beyond calculation, where (legend insisted) they would find the final scale and return, as was their destiny, to their original being: reunited with their archetype; no longer echoes. ‘And this shall be called the Time of Conference,’ said the Rose, bringing the meat boat down into a clover field of white and green. ‘The Time of Reckoning. That, Sam, is the fate of the Just.’

He had managed to reach her and now sat at her feet with his arms around the stem of the wheel. He watched her as a new force took hold of the boat. A sudden stench came up from the holds, as if something had ruptured. She struggled with the wheel. He tried to help her. She sang to whatever elements would hear her but she was suddenly powerless. She shook her head and gestured for him to relax. There was nothing more they could do.

‘We can’t go any further now, Sam,’ she said. ‘We’re not ready, I guess.’

‘Not you yet. No, no, no.’

Turning with sudden recollection they saw oddly shaped jewelled hands disappearing below. How long had the machinoix been with them?

‘She must be close to death,’ said Sam Oakenhurst.

‘Can you help her?’ asked the Rose.

It was only then that they saw the shapeless ruin of Paul Minct, its upturned mask a blazing battleground of brands, its eyes enlivened at last with the fires of hell.

The Rose made a movement with Swift Thom. There came a jolt, like a mild shockwave. Sam Oakenhurst felt water wash up his legs and reach his back.

He heard the sound of a tide as it retreated from the shore and he smelled the salt, the oily air of the coast. He opened his eyes. The boat was gone.

Eventually his vision adjusted. He understood what had happened. He lay on his side in the water, as if left there by a wave. A little above him, on the beach, the Rose was calling his name. ‘Sam! The Fault has taken the meat boat.’

‘Maybe Paul Minct achieved his ambition?’ Away in the distance were the tranquil skies which marked the Biloxi Fault. Mr Oakenhurst turned on to his back. He began to get to his feet. He shuddered at the state of his clothing and was glad there were no witnesses to their coming ashore. The Rose appeared unaffected by their adventure. Taking his hand she waded briskly through the shallows and brought them up to the tufted dunes. A light wind blew the sand in rivulets through the grass.

‘The meat boat was accepted and we were not. Whose sacrifice?’ She pointed. ‘See! We have Biloxi that way, New Orleans the other! We shall go to the Terminal, Sam. I have a purpose there.’

‘I cannot go there yet,’ he told her. ‘I must go to New Orleans. Is it too much for me to learn? Too much that is novel and incomprehensible?’

‘Ah, no, Sam. You already know it in your bones. Come on to Biloxi, mon brave. Later, maybe, you go to New Orleans, when I can come with you.’ Standing against the yellow dunes, her hair still wild, a red haze in the wind, human in form but radiating the quintessence of the rose, all its exquisite beauty, Mrs von Bek made no indirect attempt to persuade him, either by gesture or word, and for that he loved her without reserve.

‘You must go alone to Biloxi,’ he said. ‘There is a price for our salvation and I return to New Orleans to pay it.’

‘Oh, don’t go, Sam.’ Clearly she found this request almost distasteful, though she had to make it. ‘Are you sure this is nothing more than your own addiction?’

‘On my honour, I swore to help you. On my honour, I must keep my bargain with those who helped me fulfil that pledge to you.’

She accepted this in silence, but it seemed to him that he had wounded her or that she disbelieved him. He said more softly:

‘I will meet you at the Terminal. It is not my life I owe them, but my respect. I must acknowledge their sacrifice. Courageously they defied their most powerful taboos to do what I asked of them. And here we are, Rose, thanks to their courage.’

‘And ours, Sam. I would return with you now, but I, too, am bound to a promise. If I lived after my business with Mr Minct I said I would deliver a message to Mr Jack Karaquazian at the Terminal Café. So I must make my way there and, yes, I will wait for you, Sam, at least until the boredom grows intolerable.’ She smiled. ‘Yes, I will meet you again, whenever our luck will have it so. Then, I hope, you will want to come with me beyond the colour fields, beyond the universe known as The Grail, to the wonders of the Second Ether, where plurality forever holds sway. There you will discover what it is to be jugaderos and paramours, Sam. What it is to be alive! There’s more than me in this for you, Sam.’ Her lips released a sigh.

‘Well,’ he said, ‘I think you will not forget me, Rose. You know who I am.’

‘By and large, Sam.’ She turned away.

As he put the Rose, the ocean and the dunes at his back and took the broken old road towards Louisiana, her voice returned to him on the wind.

‘Ma romance, nouvelle romance. Ma romancier, muy necromancier. Ma histoire, muy histoire nouvelle. Joli boys all dansez. Joli boys all dansez. Sing for me, ole, ole. But they shall not have muy vieux carre. Joli garçon sans merci. Pauvre pierrot, mon vieux, mon brave. Petitpierrot, mon sweet savage. Le monde estfou. El mundo c’est moi.’

There was to be a final miracle: It seemed to him that the distant yell of the Biloxi Fault took fresh harmonics from the Rose’s song and amplified and modified it until for a while a vast unearthly orchestra played the old tune, told the old story of lies and truth, of betrayals and sacrifices, of quests and oaths, of love and loss and resolutions that are not always tragic. The old story which is echoed by our own.

~ * ~

This sequence began with Colour and will end with Routes. Thanks to Los Tigres del Norte (Musivisa), Mamou (MCA Records), The Movies Sound Orchestra (Yel) and the bands at Michaux’s, New Orleans.